<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Stefano's Space]]></title><description><![CDATA[Rare blog posts and some today-I-learned pills.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 06:49:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Change all Github email addresses]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/change-all-github-email-addresses</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/change-all-github-email-addresses</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 17:47:05 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I have found out that recruiters have hunted me down using the email address I have inadvertedly used to commit in Github. Unfortunatley it’s not straightforward to replace this, but here is what I’ve done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an &lt;strong&gt;empty folder&lt;/strong&gt; clone all your public repos using github API. Replace &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;YOUR-GITHUB-USERNAME&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;for SSH_URL in $(curl -s https://api.github.com/users/YOUR-GITHUB-USERNAME/repos | grep ssh_url | cut -d&amp;#39;&amp;quot;&amp;#39; -f 4)
do
    git clone $SSH_URL
done&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good time to  &lt;strong&gt;BACKUP THIS ENTIRE FOLDER&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every repo just cloned, run &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;git filter-branch&lt;/code&gt; and check the committer and author email (they are two different things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had multiple emails, and each needs to be checked for each case. This looks crazy syntactically, but still easier than an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;in&lt;/code&gt; operator in bash…
You’ll need one line to test for each case you may have used like “EmailOne”, “emailone”, “emailTwo”, etc, depending on how you tend to type this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Force push after this is done. I have commented out this line because you’ll probably want to check what happened (use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;for dir in ./*/
do
    cd $dir || exit
    pwd
    FILTER_BRANCH_SQUELCH_WARNING=1 git filter-branch -f --commit-filter &amp;#39;
    if [ &amp;quot;$GIT_COMMITTER_EMAIL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;ONE.OF@YOUR.EMAILS&amp;quot; ] \
      || [ &amp;quot;$GIT_COMMITTER_EMAIL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;ANOTHER.ONE.OF@YOUR.EMAILS&amp;quot; ] \
      || [ &amp;quot;GIT_AUTHOR_EMAIL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;ONE.OF@YOUR.EMAILS&amp;quot; ] \
      || [ &amp;quot;GIT_AUTHOR_EMAIL&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;ANOTHER.ONE.OF@YOUR.EMAILS&amp;quot; ];
    then
        GIT_COMMITTER_EMAIL=&amp;quot;i-dont-want@to-be-recuited.thank-you-very-much&amp;quot;;
        GIT_AUTHOR_EMAIL=&amp;quot;i-dont-want@to-be-recuited.thank-you-very-much&amp;quot;;
        git commit-tree &amp;quot;$@&amp;quot;;
    else
         git commit-tree &amp;quot;$@&amp;quot;;
    fi&amp;#39; HEAD
    #git push -f
    cd ..
done&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are trying to dodge recruiters maybe you should check out this project that will allow you to filter their emails in Gmail: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/StefanoChiodino/i-dont-want-to-be-recruited-thank-you-very-much&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;I don’t want to be recruited, thank you very much on Github&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Acronyms]]></title><description><![CDATA[We need to fight the urge to abbreviate everything!]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/acronyms</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/acronyms</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 21:32:04 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;One day Chris, head of devops, gave me a tour of our setup. He proudly pointed out to me how they prefer to write arguments using the long version, like &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;--allow&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;-a&lt;/code&gt;. This is to make it easier to understand the system, and thus maintaining it. It made so much sense: decrease the cognitive load, increase productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I started working for the NHS, the biggest employer in the UK, and 5th in the world, just after McDonald’s. Seems like in such a big company nobody has time to spell things out, and after more than a year I’m still struggling to catch up on some acronyms. I often come across acronyms that I never bothered or dared to ask about, and despite having developed a sense for that they represent, I still don’t know what they stand for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing code, good sense dictates you should call your variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;pageTitle&lt;/code&gt;, rather than &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;pt&lt;/code&gt;. So why is it ok to abbreviate &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;GPES Data for Pandemic Planning and Research&lt;/code&gt; in a nested acronym to GDPPR?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a business writing course recently, and one of the key points was that you have to write for your audience. Look, I get it. I review a lot of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;merge requests&lt;/code&gt;, and the temptation to call them &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;MR&lt;/code&gt; is strong, but think about your audience. Are you in a group chat with your Product Owner and the New Starter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use all the acronyms you are confident your colleagues know, when you are writing to them in private. Maximise understanding everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Notes on book Never Split the Difference]]></title><description><![CDATA[My notes on the book Never Split the Difference by Christopher Voss and Tahl Raz]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/notes-on-boo-never-split-the-difference</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/notes-on-boo-never-split-the-difference</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 21:36:25 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It’s important to &lt;strong&gt;smile&lt;/strong&gt; when talking on the phone, it sounds different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mirror&lt;/strong&gt; is the technique of repeating the last three words, or the last critical one. It makes the other party feel in tune with yourself and push them to continue talking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pause&lt;/strong&gt; 4 seconds, especially after a mirror, to let it sink in and force a reaction. This may lead to the other party disclose more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labelling&lt;/strong&gt; is the technique of describing how the other party feels. It helps clarify the matters, adds a chance for a pause, and shows that we are listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheap negotiators want to hear yes. Good ones want to &lt;strong&gt;hear no&lt;/strong&gt;, because when a party says no they feel they are in control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put yourself in the other party’s place and &lt;strong&gt;understand&lt;/strong&gt; their situation. You’ll know what to offer, and what you can ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deadlines&lt;/strong&gt; cut two ways. The pressure to make a deal is on any party ware of a deadline. If you have a deadline let the other party know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are irrationality more concerned with losses than gains. Mention what the other party stands to lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”&lt;strong&gt;Fair&lt;/strong&gt;” is one of the strongest words. Use it to propose you are meeting the other party in the middle, or that they aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frame&lt;/strong&gt; the negotiation so that what you ask actually seems convenient. E.g. for a salary negotiation ask for a range where you wish to receive the lower bound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always try to get &lt;strong&gt;non monetary incentives&lt;/strong&gt;. This also shows that you have reached the limit of how much money you are willing to bargain. Use towards the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Round numbers seem artificial and subject to bargain. We perceive &lt;strong&gt;precise numbers&lt;/strong&gt; as elaborated and more sticky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;open ended calibrated questions&lt;/strong&gt; like “how am I supposed to do that?“. They start with how or what, deliver them with calm, and follow by a pause. Open ended means they need more than a yes or no answer. Calibrated means you need to adjust them to a particular scenario. These questions provoke a shift in the position of the other party, or at least more information. Instead of saying “don’t go!” say “what do you hope to achieve by going?“. “Why” almost always comes across as an accusation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep &lt;strong&gt;emotions&lt;/strong&gt; in check at all times. Make sure to pause. Understand that negotiation is about emotions as much as rationality. Keep the goal in sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Listening&lt;/strong&gt; is being in control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A negotiator role is to establish what to do, how to do it, and make sure it’s done. For example lead from a verbal agreement to a contract, and from there to a payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summarise&lt;/strong&gt; the other party situation until you hear “that’s right”. If they say “you are right” then it means they feel you forced the plan on them. “I’ll try” indicates not enough buy-in. If you happen to hear these dive back in with calibrated questions until resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be aware of decision killers as much as decision makers. Other stakeholders are sometimes not obvious, probe to get to know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self esteem, pride, images, etc are often as important as money. Remember &lt;strong&gt;it’s not a rational process&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the other party’s name but not too much. Also use your own name if possible. It all makes it more relatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say “no” without using the word, with phrases like “how am I supposed to do that?”, “your offer is very generous, I’m sorry that just doesn’t work for me”, “I’m sorry but I’m afraid I can’t do that”, and “I’m sorry, no”. “No” should have a gentle downward inflection to not sound aggressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going in a negotiation set limits and work within those. &lt;strong&gt;Never get angry&lt;/strong&gt;, even tho sounding a bit angry can be beneficial at times, but often comes across fake. Never consider the other party the problem: &lt;strong&gt;the negotiation is the problem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the &lt;strong&gt;Ackerman model&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your target price (your goal).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set your first offer at 65 percent of your target price.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculate three raises of decreasing increments (to 85, 95, and 100 percent).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use lots of empathy and different ways of saying “No” to get the other side to counter before you increase your offer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When calculating the final amount, use precise, non round numbers, it gives the number credibility and weight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On your final number, throw in a non monetary item (that they probably don’t want) to show you’re at your limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black swans&lt;/strong&gt; are events you thought were impossible, and never consider.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Notes on Coursera Business Writing Course]]></title><description><![CDATA[My notes on a business writing course]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/business-writing-course-notes</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/business-writing-course-notes</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:40:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity above all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t waste the reader’s time. “If I had more time, I would have written a shorter letter” - Blaise Pascal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The look makes a difference. Make your text easier on the eyes. Use bullet points, white space, shorter sentences, margins, boldface, etc .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be smart: don’t try to sound smart. Avoid jargon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be the authority: don’t use “I’m thinking”, “in my opinion”, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scaffold well to write well. Structure you text in 3 phases: say what you want to say, say it, repeat it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One idea per paragraph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every paragraph should start with a strong sentence on the paragraph’s topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with your purpose, not the motivation or justification for it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The text may become too mechanical after revising. Keep your “voice” in your document by reading it out loud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you find duplicate sentences, cut out the negative sounding ones first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grammar matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grammar - I vs me: use I if it’s a subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attribute modifiers like adjectives need to one of the nouns. Make them adjacent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouns are words that take the place of nouns, like I, he, them. They refer to the closest antecedent noun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of the writing from your reader perspective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut adjectives and adverbs; qualifiers and amplifiers; “in fact”, “possibly”, “generally”, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut out generalities like “everyone knows”, they often include the words: all everybody, everywhere, etc. You may need to rewrite sentences to make them more specific if they include words like: some, somebody, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use an active voice: “Bob did X”, not “X was done by Bob”. Passive voice is longer, less clear, and less emphatic. But it’s acceptable in scientific papers because it sounds more impartial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limit verbs “to be” and “to have”. Including forms is, am, are, were, was, will be, have, has, had, have been and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ref: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/writing-for-business/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/writing-for-business/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Business Writing course on Coursera&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why are plants green?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Most of the sun energy is in the green wavelength, why do plants not absorb it?]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/why-are-plants-green</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/why-are-plants-green</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 08:11:06 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Most of the sun’s energy is in the green wavelength, however that’s exactly what the plants bounce back, as chlorophyll of type a and b absorbs light in the red and blue spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was thought that collecting too much of the available wavelength could harm the plant (think of how hot black surfaces can become). However it has recently been discovered that plants are trying to optimise for a steady flux of energy, because flickers in the energy collected can cause energy failures or tissue damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the long run evolution selects for performances, but also stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Reddit /r/til&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ref: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/why-are-plants-green-to-reduce-the-noise-in-photosynthesis-20200730/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.quantamagazine.org/why-are-plants-green-to-reduce-the-noise-in-photosynthesis-20200730/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[North Korea is a necrocracy]]></title><description><![CDATA[Kim Il-sung died in '94 but it's been nominated eternal President of the Republic]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/north-korea-is-a-necrocracy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/north-korea-is-a-necrocracy</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 13:42:15 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Kim Il-sung died in ‘94 but it’s been nominated eternal President of the Republic, making the country’s system a necrocracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Reddit /r/til&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ref.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/necrocracy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/necrocracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[RAS Syndrome]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Redundant Acronym Syndrome]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/ras-syndrome</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/ras-syndrome</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 14:21:28 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I recall a friend complaining about “PAT test”, because PAT already stands for Portable Appliance Test, so adding test at the end was redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve eventually came across the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAS_syndrome&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;SAR syndrome&lt;/a&gt;, which is a self-referential name for this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other common cases of SAR syndrome are PIN and VIN numbers, ATM machine, HIV virus, LCD display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acronyms suffering from SAR syndromes are widely accepted as the redundancy adds clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Skeuomorph]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/skeuomorph</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/skeuomorph</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 07:37:31 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A skeuomorph is an object that maintained design cues that have become non functional. For example the tiny handle on maple syrup bottle is to retain the distinctive appearance of the much bigger jugs maple syrup was once stored in. Other examples are many icons on modern mobile phones and computers, light bulbs in the shape of candles, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Googling for the reason why maple syrup bottles have a tiny handle.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Monocote vs dicot plants]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/monocote-vs-dicot-plants</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/monocote-vs-dicot-plants</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 19:49:56 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Dicots and monocots differs on several more features other than the one that gives them their names: the number of cotyledon (leafs) in their embryo. Monocots have parallel veins in their leafs, which usually means elongate leafs as well,  complexly arranged vascular system, fibrous roots, and floral parts usually in multiple of three. Dicots have a network of branching veins, a vascular system arranged in rings, a taproot system (a long main root), and floral parts usually arranged in multiple of four or five.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Coursera’s Understanding Plants - Part II: Fundamentals of Plant Biology Week 2
2.1 Plant organs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/4927r/2-1-plant-organs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/4927r/2-1-plant-organs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Xylem]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/xyle</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/xyle</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 23:10:51 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Xylem are tubes that allows water and substances to go through a plant. They are made of cells that die through apoptosis (programmed cell death). This process thickens the side walls, remove the top and bottom ones, and progressively kills the cell, leaving a tube of all those cell walls in their place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Coursera’s Understanding Plants - Part II: Fundamentals of Plant Biology Week 1
1.8 Vascular tissue - xylem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/jZRR7/1-8-vascular-tissue-xylem&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/jZRR7/1-8-vascular-tissue-xylem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Plasmodesma]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/plasmodesma</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/plasmodesma</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 22:50:16 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Plasmodesma is a narrow thread of cytoplasm that passes through the cell walls of adjacent plant cells and allows communication between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Coursera’s Understanding Plants - Part II: Fundamentals of Plant Biology Week 1
1.7 The vacuole and plasmodesmata&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/gwRmz/1-7-the-vacuole-and-plasmodesmata&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/plant-biology/lecture/gwRmz/1-7-the-vacuole-and-plasmodesmata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fundamental attribution error]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/fundamental-attribution-error</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/fundamental-attribution-error</guid><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 17:24:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental attribution error is the tendency for people to attribute far too much importance to personality rather than situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Coursera - Yale’s Introduction to Psychology &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/introduction-psychology/lecture/Urm4G/attribution&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://www.coursera.org/learn/introduction-psychology/lecture/Urm4G/attribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[ A life is valued 10 million dollars]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/a-life-is-valued-10-million-dollars</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/a-life-is-valued-10-million-dollars</guid><pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 22:08:15 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the USA the value of a life has been estimated to be worth 10 million USD. This was initially much smaller, being just what a person would earn for the rest of his life, in average. It was later adjusted to reflect what a human life is worth, other than just work, by calculating how much the market values the danger of more risky job to be worth, but also what is it worth to their dears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Planet Money podcast, episode “Lives vs the economy”.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Conjuntion fallacy]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/conjuction-fallacy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/conjuction-fallacy</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Conjunction fallacy occurs when it is assumed that specific conditions are more probable than a single general one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Rationality Course&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via: Harvard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: 45 minutes in &lt;a href=&quot;https://harvard.hosted.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=a780e65f-e1d0-47a2-97c4-ab3b0140edfb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://harvard.hosted.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=a780e65f-e1d0-47a2-97c4-ab3b0140edfb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Alkaline battery]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/alkaline-battery</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/alkaline-battery</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;To produce an Amazon basic alkaline battery may require 100 times more energy than what the battery can actually produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: The Verge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via: Apple News&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Asia after World War Two]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/asia-after-world-war-two</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/asia-after-world-war-two</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After the Second World War forecasts were that Asia was going to be a trouble area because it was poorer that Africa and without the same amount of resources. Turned out that labour force and education can overcome that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Masters in business podcast&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Probability can be subjective]]></title><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/probability-can-be-subjective</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/probability-can-be-subjective</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If I flip a coin and look at the result in secret, being heads, then the chances that it’s heads it’s 100% for me, but 50% for everybody else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Rationality Course&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via: Harvard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;URL: 32 minutes in &lt;a href=&quot;https://harvard.hosted.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=a780e65f-e1d0-47a2-97c4-ab3b0140edfb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://harvard.hosted.panopto.com/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=a780e65f-e1d0-47a2-97c4-ab3b0140edfb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Pragmatic Programmer - Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[My notes from the book "The Pragmatic Programmer" by Andrew Hunt and David Thomas]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-pragmatic-programmer-book-notes</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-pragmatic-programmer-book-notes</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 08:54:24 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Written by Andrew Hunt and David Thomas. Originally published October 1999. 25th printing, 10th Feb version. 320 Pages. ISBN: 978-0-2016-1622-4. Publisher: Addison-Wesley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book invites the reader to progress in whatever order, as reading from front to back is not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the book you are prompted to visit other parts to expand on an topic. At the end of each section you are sometimes prompted with challenges that make you reflect on what you just read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming is a craft. At its simplest, it comes down to getting a computer to do what you want it to do (or what your user wants it to do).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Makes a Pragmatic Programmer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Early adopter/fast adapter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inquisitive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical thinker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realistic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jack of all trades.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Care About Your Craft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Kaizen” is a Japanese term that captures the conceptof continuously making many small improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-1---a-pragmatic-philosophy&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-1---a-pragmatic-philosophy&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 1   a pragmatic philosophy permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;CHAPTER 1 - A PRAGMATIC PHILOSOPHY&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cat Ate My Source Code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 3: Provide Options, Don’t Make Lame Excuses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software Entropy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While software development is immune from almost all physical laws,entropy hits us hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 4: Don’t Live with Broken Windows […] Don’t let entropy win.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even with a fire to put out, don’t be the first to break a window!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stone Soup and Boiled Frogs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 5: Be a Catalyst for Change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 6: Remember the Big Picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenge: Sometimes deception is needed to catalyse change, so don’t use it to do harm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good-Enough Software&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If trade-offs are possible ask for them: how good is this software meant to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 7: Make Quality a Requirements Issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often great software today is better than perfect software tomorrow. (MVP, agile)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenge: Think about the software that you use. Is it perfect? Would you rather wait for the “perfect” version?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your Knowledge Portfolio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An investment in knowledge always pays the best interest. (Benjamin Franklin)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge in software is an expiring asset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is an asset and can be treated like an investment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversify your knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn some new up-and-coming tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give up on old tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn one new language every year (seems a lot). Different languages will force you to think differently. E.g.: Rust forces you not to use nulls and think of return types as Option and Result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read a technical book each quarter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take classes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participate in local groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experiment with different environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stay current online and offline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It doesn’t matter what use you are going to make of your new knowledge, the process of learning will expand your thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 9: Critically Analyze What You Read and Hear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to ask for knowledge: be specific, frame the question carefully and politely, once your question is written down look one more time for the answer, be patient, give back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communicate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“A good idea is an orphan without effective communication.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Plan what you want to say. Write an outline”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask yourself about your audience the WISDOM acrostic (what, interest, sophisticated, detail, own, motivate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chose a style (short, long, factual, funny, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it look good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you want people to listen to you listen to them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 10: It’s Both What You Say and the Way You Say It&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails are forever&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-2---a-pragmatic-approach&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-2---a-pragmatic-approach&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 2   a pragmatic approach permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 2 - A Pragmatic Approach&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Evils of Duplication&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 11: DRY—Don’t Repeat Yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It isn’t a question of whether you’ll remember: it’s a question of when you’ll forget.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplication can be due to developers feeling there is no other way, without realising it, for laziness or because different developers produced by coincidence the same functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imposed duplication can be worked around by using a pre-processor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inadverted duplication can be due to unnormalised data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments are knowledge too and take part in duplication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performances may tempt developers to duplicate, however this is just a cheap solution (e.g. some calculated data can be stored due to the expense of being produced, however care needs to be taken to update it if any of the inputs changes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 12: Make It Easy to Reuse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ease or reusing functionality is a step towards de-duplication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orthogonality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often overlooked but core concept of other methods and techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refers to the decoupling of things so that moving on one line your position projected on the other doesn’t change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 13: Eliminate Effects Between Unrelated Things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity gain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Changes are localized, so development time and testing time are reduced”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote reuse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s easier to combine orthogonal components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reduce Risk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compartamentalise problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robustness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably better tested as tests are easier to write.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3rd party changes have less effect on your system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Layering is a powerful way to achieve orthogonality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test for orthogonality are easy: ask yourself how many parts of the software would be affected if you had to change any other part. It should be one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit testing and documentation is an easy winner when code is orthogonal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OOP can provide with tools for more orthogonality, but also more chances for less of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reversibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Requirements, users, and hardware change faster than we can get the software developed.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 14: There Are No Final Decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“keep decisions soft and pliable”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracer Bullets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracer bullets are used to correct the aim of fire arms in the dark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 15: Use Tracer Bullets to Find the Target&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like prototyping but keeping the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build skeleton of a system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prototypes and Post-it Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prototypes don’t need to be on code. Could be on post-its or whiteboard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 16: Prototype to Learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can prototype anything new, risky, experimental, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer high level language, stick with an at least similar language if testing for performances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architecture wise prototyping is valuable to check for coupling, responsibilities and collaborations of components, interface definition, possible duplications, data access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make very clear to everybody that it’s disposable code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domain Languages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 17: Program Close to the Problem Domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come up with high level languages to help define a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different part of a problem may require their own language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a syntax first with a notation such as BNF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools such as bison and yacc can convert well defined languages to programming languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimating&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice estimating to be able to get a feel for order go magnitudes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 18: Estimate to Avoid Surprises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first question when asked for an estimation should be “how accurate?”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The smaller the granularity of the estimations the greater the assumption of degree of accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Duration&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Quote estimate in&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1–15 days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;days&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3–8 weeks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;weeks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8–30 weeks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;months&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30+ weeks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;think hard before giving an estimate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The easiest way to improve on you estimate is to draw from other peoples experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a model for the estimate e.g. variants, building blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Your experience will tell you when to stop refining.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the estimate becomes more complex you’ll want to hedge your answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take notes of you estimate and the actual values. Investigate when there is a substantial difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 19: Iterate the Schedule with the Code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“What to Say When Asked for an Estimate? You say ‘I’ll get back to you.’”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-3---the-basic-tools&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-3---the-basic-tools&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 3   the basic tools permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 3 - The Basic Tools&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with basic tools then adopt new ones. Go back to to the basics from time to time to sharpen your skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Power of Plain Text&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 20: Keep Knowledge in Plain Text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cons: slower to computer, takes more space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pros: easier to remember the meaning of data, flexible, easier to test (e.g.: change data without recompiling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shell Games&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GUI are best for simple operation, shell are more powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 21: Use the Power of Command Shells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power Editing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 22: Use a Single Editor Well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that your editor of choice is available on multiple platforms/OS/shells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source Code Control&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Code Control Systems allows for decentralisation, collaboration, backup, statistics, undoing changes, compartmentalisation,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 23: Always Use Source Code Control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use SCCS for everything, not just code. [This may be a bit anachronistic now that a similar effect can be achieved with Google Docs and the like]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SCCS allows for automated and repeatable builds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debugging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Embrace the fact that debugging is just problem solving, and attack itas such.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 24: Fix the Problem, Not the Blame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 25: Don’t Panic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resist the urge to fix just the symptoms you see. […] Always try to discover the root cause of a problem, not just this particular appearance of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bug reporting isn’t an exact science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accuracy in bug reports is further diminished when they come through a third party&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isolate the steps to reproduce the bug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the process of elimination assume you are at fault before a third party. If a third party is at fault you’ll still probably need to isolate the problem as much as possible for a bug report.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 26: “select” Isn’t Broken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 27: Don’t Assume It—Prove It&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it took a long time to fix try to find ways to make it easier for the next time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the bug came from one person’s misunderstanding see if anyone else had that misunderstanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text Manipulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 28: Learn a Text Manipulation Language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code Generators&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 29: Write Code That Writes Code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passive code generators produce source code that becomes part of the project. They don’t always have to be totally accurate. [e.g.: templating]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Active code generators helps to comply with the DRY principle  and are meant to be used continuously to feed changes from the input files to the output ones [e.g.: asp.net transforms]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-4---pragmatic-paranoia&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-4---pragmatic-paranoia&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 4   pragmatic paranoia permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 4 - Pragmatic Paranoia&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 30: You Can’t Write Perfect Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be defensive of other peoples code, and of your own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design by Contract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Dealing with computer systems is hard. Dealing with people is even harder.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Bertrand Meyer developed the concept of Design by Contractfor the language Eiffel.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In DBC there are 3 expectations that needs to be met: preconditions, postconditions and class invariants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 31: Design with Contracts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Be strict in what you will accept beforeyou begin, and promise as little as possible in return”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dead Programs Tell No Lies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 32: Crash Early&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“many times, crashing your program is the bestthing you can do”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assertive Programming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 33: If It Can’t Happen, Use Assertions to Ensure That It Won’t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most “assert” should be left in the code even in production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asserts should have no side effects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When to Use Exceptions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“One of the problems with exceptions is knowing when to use them. Webelieve that exceptions should rarely be used as part of a program’snormal flow; exceptions should be reserved for unexpected events”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 34: Use Exceptions for Exceptional Problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to Balance Resources&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 35: Finish What You Start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t couple code with shared resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Deallocate resources in the opposite order to that in which you allocate them.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a series of resources are allocated in more than one place try to allocate them in the same order to avoid deadlocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is always a good idea to invest in writing code to check the resource balance, like wrappers that tracks resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-5---bend-or-break&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-5---bend-or-break&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 5   bend or break permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 5 - Bend, or Break&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;26&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decoupling and the Law of Demeter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write ‘shy’ code: don’t reveal yourself to others and don’t interact with too many people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organise code in cells and limit their interaction like organisations that value privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 36: Minimize Coupling Between Modules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The Law of Demeter for functions states that any method of anobject should call only methods belonging to: itself, any parameters that were passed in to the method, any objects it created and any directly held component objects”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metaprogramming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the details out of the code to make it soft and configurable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metadata is data about data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 37: Configure, Don’t Integrate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 38: Put Abstractions in Code, Details in Metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing configuration out of the code allows for decoupling, abstraction, configuring application more easily and changing the configuration without compilation step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide if it’s worth implementing a mechanism to reload the configuration on the fly. Consider how long-running the application will be and how quick and easy restarting it would be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temporal Coupling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time is often ignored in software architecture. Time aspects to consider are concurrency and ordering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow needs to be modelled with UML activity diagram or similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 39: Analyze Workflow to Improve Concurrency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hungry consumer model consists of workers getting tasks from a queue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 40: Design Using Services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 41: Always Design for Concurrency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding concurrency to a system that has not been designed as such is very difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s Just a View&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use events to decouple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dispatching events from a single routine cause more coupling. Use the publish/subscribe pattern.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 42: Separate Views from Models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Model-View-Controller (MVC) to separate the model from both the GUI and the controls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MVC typically exists in a GUI context, but the same concept on segregation of concerns can be applied to any kind of programming: Model is the data, the view is a way of interpreting the data, and the controller feeds the data to the view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blackboards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A blackboard system is a data storage that allows actors to asynchronously work on shared data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blackboard systems became popular in artificial intelligence, where problems are large and complex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 43: Use Blackboards to Coordinate Workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-6---while-you-are-coding&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-6---while-you-are-coding&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 6   while you are coding permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 6 - While You Are Coding&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;31&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming by Coincidence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“We should avoid pro-gramming by coincidence—relying on luck and accidental successes—in favor of programming deliberately.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons why not to program by coincidence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May not be really working but only looking like it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May be an accidental boundary condition and not work all the times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Undocumented behaviour subject to change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibly slower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More error prone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Assumptions that aren’t based on well-established facts are the bane of all projects.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 44: Don’t Program by Coincidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To program deliberately you should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware of what you are doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware of what you are going to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proceed from a plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t rely on accidents or assumptions. Assume the worse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document your assumptions (e.g.: design by contract).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test your assumptions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on the important parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t let existing code/functionality dictate what you are doing. Refactor if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Algorithm Speed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s important to estimate speed of algorithms when not linear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The O notation determines the upper bounds of algorithms. Because of this it does incur in some precision loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The big O notation is also uses to model memory or other resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should keep in mind the big O notation and ask yourself what scale are you working on to understand what the impact will be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 45: Estimate the Order of Your Algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are unsure on the efficiency of your code then run it a few time with different inputs and plot the results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 46: Test Your Estimates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes is not all about the efficiency: if the inputs are known small it could be better to have easier to write and debug code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be wary of premature optimisations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactoring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building software is organic, much more like gardening than building constructions, but business people are much more comfortable with the latter metaphor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Rewriting, reworking, and re-architecting code is collectively known as refactoring.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t hesitate to refactor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good reasons for refactoring: duplication, non-orthodoganl design, outdated knowledge, performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time pressure is often used as an excuse for not refactoring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 47: Refactor Early, Refactor Often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin Fowler tips on refactoring: don’t add functionality while refactoring; Make sure you are covered by tests and run them often; Take short, deliberate steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code That’s Easy to Test&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The term “Software IC” (Integrated Circuit) seems to have been invented in 1986 by Cox and Novobilski in their Objective-C book Object-Oriented Programming” and it refers to the practice of writing modular software that can be tested just like individual chips that are then composed together on a board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can test against the contract.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 48: Design to Test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit tests provide examples on how to use your code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the tests often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use test harnesses (JUnit, xUnit, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debugging may be necessary in production environment, in this case log files, hot keys sequences or web servers to reveal status messages may be the best option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Format log files correctly to help with parson and for readability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Testing is more cultural than technical”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 49: Test Your Software, or Your Users Will&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evil Wizards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 50: Don’t Use Wizard Code You Don’t Understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers routinely use things that don’t understand, but wizard’s code (boilerplate) is not abstracted away like a library or a processor mechanism, it’s interwoven with the developer code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-7---before-the-project&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-7---before-the-project&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 7   before the project permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 7 - Before the Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a fine line between specifying too much (analysis paralysis) and not enough (not being ready).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Requirements Pit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Requirements rarely lie on the surface.Normally, they’re buried deep beneath layers of assumptions, miscon-ceptions, and politics.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 51: Don’t Gather Requirements—Dig for Them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“A requirement is a statement of somethingthat needs to be accomplished”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document policies should be separated from requirements. E.g. only employee’s supervisors may see employee’s records should be defined as the need for access control in the requirements and specify who can access what(the policies/metadata/configuration) in another document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s important to discover the underlying reason why users do a par-ticular thing, rather than just the way they currently do it. At the endof the day, your development has to solve their business problem, notjust meet their stated requirements. Documenting the reasons behind requirements will give your team invaluable information when makingdaily implementation decisions.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A simple technique to get the requirements right is to do the work of your future users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 52: Work with a User to Think Like a User&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t over-specify. Requirements are needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 53: Abstractions Live Longer than Details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 54: Use a Project Glossary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the glossary easily available (e.g., web resource).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving Impossible Puzzles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 55: Don’t Think Outside the Box—Find the Box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever faced with a puzzle that seems impossible ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Is there an easier way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Are you trying to solve the right problem, or have you been distracted by a peripheral technicality?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Why is this thing a problem?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“What is it that’s making it so hard to solve?Does it have to be done this way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Does it have to be done at all?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not Until You’re Ready&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 56: Listen to Nagging Doubts—Start When You’re Ready&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listen to your instincts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If insure if waiting for the right moment or procrastinating then start a prototype, then you’ll know to start if you fee like you are wasting your time. If prototyping is creating new questions and you encounter snags on the way then you know you weren’t ready.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Specification Trap&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Program specification is the process of taking a requirement and reducing it down to the point where a programmer’s skill can take over.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The specification is a record for future developers and an agreements with the user, an implicit contact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many designers find it difficult to stop specifying. Is naive to assume that the perfect specification can be achieved, and even if the client signs it off you can’t guarantee that it’s is what they actually need and they won’t want to change it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 57: Some Things Are Better Done than Described&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a lose specification allows developers to work their way around certain problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“spec- ification and implementation are simply different aspects of the same process—an attempt to capture and codify a requirement.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over-specifying incurs in diminishing or even negative returns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circles and Arrows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 58: Don’t Be a Slave to Formal Methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Never underestimate the cost of adopting new tools and methods.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 59: Expensive Tools Do Not Produce Better Designs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;chapter-8---pragmatic-projects&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-8---pragmatic-projects&quot; aria-label=&quot;chapter 8   pragmatic projects permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chapter 8 - Pragmatic Projects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;41&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pragmatic Teams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Teams as a whole should not tolerate broken windows” (see 1.2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code quality shouldn’t be delegated to one or some members of the team, it should be everybody’s responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The boiling frog problem is even more common in teams. The dilution of responsibilities makes it easier for the scope to increase and the time scales to decrease. Maybe appoint a person to be in charge of this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communication is important for individuals as much as for teams, which should comunicate as one. It help to generate a branding for teams, to give them identity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A team member could be appointed as librarian to help with the duplication of documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s a mistake to organise teams based on jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 60: Organize Around Functionality, Not Job Functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“The project needs at least two “heads”—one technical, the other administrative.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“A great way to ensure both consistency and accuracy is to automate everything the team does.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubiquitous Automation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Manual procedures leave consistency up to chance; repeatabilityisn’t guaranteed, especially if aspects of the procedure are open to interpretation by different people.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 61: Don’t Use Manual Procedures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compiling the project should be reliable and repeatable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automation doesn’t only apply to code, but also administrative tasks and documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruthless Testing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Most developers hate testing.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 62: Test Early. Test Often. Test Automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 63 Coding Ain’t Done ’Til All the Tests Run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit testing ensures the functionality of a self-contained unit of code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration testings verifies the units of code works well together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Validation and verification tests make sure you are building what the client wants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resource exhaustion, errors and recovery needs to be tested too. There are several resources that you can test the lack of: screen resolution, network bandwidth, disk bandwidth, system clock precision, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance testing include stress testing and load testing. Specialised hardware or software may be necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usability testing are run by real users in real environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code quality can be partially tested by measuring cyclomatic complexity, inheritance fan-in and fan-out, response set (number of functions directly invokedby methods of the class) and class coupling ratios. Some of these can only be used by comparison to other pieces of code and so standard deviation is often used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression testing compares the outcome of the current test to previous ones or known values. E.g.: making sure bugs don’t resurface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test data may be real-world one and be collected by competitors systems, or synthetic one that is generated to obtain a big quantity of it or test boundary conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GUI tests can be complicated to maintain if the interface is being worked on. In this situation having decoupled code help in reducing the scope of the GUI tests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 64: Use Saboteurs to Test Your Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code coverage can help understand if enough have been tested. However, testing 100% of the code lines doesn’t mean perfect testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 65: Test State Coverage, Not Code Coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code should be tested as soon as any production code exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test should be run before checking the code in the source repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When bugs are found a test should be written to avoid it resurfacing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 66: Find Bugs Once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s All Writing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Pragmatic Programmers embrace documentation as an integral part ofthe overall development process.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 67: Treat English as Just Another Programming Language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 68: Build Documentation In, Don’t Bolt It On.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Code should have comments,but too many comments can be just as bad as too few.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Even worse than meaningless names are misleading names.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t add to the comments information that can be determined by tools. Like usages, and revision history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great Expectations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A project is successful if it meets the expectations of the clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 69: Gently Exceed Your Users’ Expectations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surprise the users, in a good way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pride and Prejudice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIP 70: Sign Your Work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take pride in your work but don’t become prejudiced of it in favour of your coworkers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;quick-reference-guide&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#quick-reference-guide&quot; aria-label=&quot;quick reference guide permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Quick reference guide&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Care About Your Craft&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why spend your life developing software unless you care about doing it well?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think! About Your Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn off the autopilot and take control. Constantly critique and appraise your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Provide Options, Don’t Make Lame Excuses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of excuses, provide options. Don’t say it can’t be done; explain what can be done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Live with Broken Windows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix bad designs, wrong decisions, and poor code when you see them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be a Catalyst for Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can’t force change on people. Instead, show them how the future might be and help them participate in creating it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the Big Picture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t get so engrossed in the details that you forget to check what’s happening around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make Quality a Requirements Issue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Involve your users in determining the project’s real quality requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invest Regularly in Your Knowledge Portfolio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make learning a habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critically Analyze What You Read and Hear&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t be swayed by vendors, media hype, or dogma. Analyze information in terms of you and your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s Both What You Say and theWay You Say It&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s no point in having great ideas if you don’t communicate them effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DRY—Don’t Repeat Yourself&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every piece of knowledge must have a single, unambiguous, authoritative representation within a system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make It Easy to Reuse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it’s easy to reuse, people will. Create an environment that supports reuse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eliminate Effects Between Unrelated Things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design components that are self-contained, independent, and have a single, well-defined purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There Are No Final Decisions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No decision is cast in stone. Instead, consider each as being written in the sand at the beach, and plan for change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Tracer Bullets to Find the Target&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracer bullets let you home in on your target by trying things and seeing how close they land.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prototype to Learn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prototyping is a learning experience. Its value lies not in the code you produce, but in the lessons you learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Program Close to the Problem Domain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design and code in your user’s language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimate to Avoid Surprises&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimate before you start. You’ll spot potential problems up front. 19. Iterate the Schedule with the Code Use experience you gain as you implement to refine the project time scales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep Knowledge in Plain Text&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plain text won’t become obsolete. It helps leverage your work and simplifies debugging and testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the Power of Command Shells&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the shell when graphical user interfaces don’t cut it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a Single Editor Well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The editor should be an extension of your hand; make sure your editor is configurable, extensible, and programmable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always Use Source Code Control&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source code control is a time machine for your work—you can go back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fix the Problem, Not the Blame&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It doesn’t really matter whether the bug is your fault or someone else’s—it is still your problem, and it still needs to be fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Panic When Debugging&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a deep breath and THINK! about what could be causing the bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“select” Isn’t Broken&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is rare to find a bug in the OS or the compiler, or even a third-party product or library. The bug is most likely in the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Assume It—Prove It&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prove your assumptions in the actual environment— with real data and boundary conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn a Text Manipulation Language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You spend a large part of each day working with text. Why not have the computer do some of it for you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write Code That Writes Code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code generators increase your productivity and help avoid duplication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You Can’t Write Perfect Software&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software can’t be perfect. Protect your code and users from the inevitable errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design with Contracts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use contracts to document and verify that code does no more and no less than it claims to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crash Early&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dead program normally does a lot less damage than a crippled one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Assertions to Prevent the Impossible&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assertions validate your assumptions. Use them to protect your code from an uncertain world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Exceptions for Exceptional Problems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exceptions can suffer from all the readability and maintainability problems of classic spaghetti code. Reserve exceptions for exceptional things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finish What You Start&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where possible, the routine or object that allocates a resource should be responsible for deallocating it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimize Coupling Between Modules&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid coupling by writing “shy” code and applying the Law of Demeter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configure, Don’t Integrate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement technology choices for an application as configuration options, not through integration or engineering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put Abstractions in Code, Details in Metadata&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Program for the general case, and put the specifics outside the compiled code base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analyze Workflow to Improve Concurrency&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploit concurrency in your user’s workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design Using Services&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design in terms of services—independent, concurrent objects behind well-defined, consistent interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always Design for Concurrency&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow for concurrency, and you’ll design cleaner interfaces with fewer assumptions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separate Views from Models&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gain flexibility at low cost by designing your application in terms of models and views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Blackboards to Coordinate Workflow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use blackboards to coordinate disparate facts and agents, while maintaining independence and isolation among participants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Program by Coincidence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rely only on reliable things. Beware of accidental complexity, and don’t confuse a happy coincidence with a purposeful plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimate the Order of Your Algorithms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a feel for how long things are likely to take before you write code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test Your Estimates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical analysis of algorithms doesn’t tell you everything. Try timing your code in its target environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactor Early, Refactor Often&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just as you might weed and rearrange a garden rewrite, rework, and re-architect code when it needs it. Fix the root of the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design to Test&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start thinking about testing before you write a line of code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test Your Software, or Your Users Will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test ruthlessly. Don’t make your users find bugs for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t UseWizard Code You Don’t Understand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wizards can generate reams of code. Make sure you understand all of it before you incorporate it into your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Gather Requirements—Dig for Them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Requirements rarely lie on the surface. They’re buried deep beneath layers of assumptions, misconceptions, and politics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work with a User to Think Like a User&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s the best way to gain insight into how the system will really be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstractions Live Longer than Details&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invest in the abstraction, not the implementation. Abstractions can survive the barrage of changes from different implementations and new technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a Project Glossary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and maintain a single source of all the specific terms and vocabulary for a project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Think Outside the Box—Find the Box&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When faced with an impossible problem, identify the real constraints. Ask yourself: “Does it have to be done this way? Does it have to be done at all?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start When You’re Ready&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You’ve been building experience all your life. Don’t ignore niggling doubts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Things Are Better Done than Described&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t fall into the specification spiral—at some point you need to start coding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Be a Slave to Formal Methods&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t blindly adopt any technique without putting it into the context of your development practices and capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costly Tools Don’t Produce Better Designs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beware of vendor hype, industry dogma, and the aura of the price tag. Judge tools on their merits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organize Teams Around Functionality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t separate designers from coders, testers from data modelers. Build teams the way you build code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t Use Manual Procedures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A shell script or batch file will execute the same instructions, in the same order, time after time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test Early. Test Often. Test Automatically&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tests that run with every build are much more effective than test plans that sit on a shelf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding Ain’t Done ’Til All the Tests Run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;’Nuff said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Saboteurs to Test Your Testing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce bugs on purpose in a separate copy of the source to verify that testing will catch them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test State Coverage, Not Code Coverage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify and test significant program states. Just testing lines of code isn’t enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find Bugs Once&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once a human tester finds a bug, it should be the last time a human tester finds that bug. Automatic tests should check for it from then on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English is Just a Programming Language&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write documents as you would write code: honor the DRY principle, use metadata, MVC, automatic generation, and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build Documentation In, Don’t Bolt It On&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation created separately from code is less likely to be correct and up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gently Exceed Your Users’ Expectations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come to understand your users’ expectations, then deliver just that little bit more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sign Your Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Craftsmen of an earlier age were proud to sign their work. You should be, too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Humane Typography in the Digital Age]]></title><description><![CDATA[An Essay on Typography by Eric Gill takes the reader back to the year 1930. The year when a conflict between two worlds came to its term. The machines of the industrial world finally took over the handicrafts.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-first-transition&quot;&gt;The first transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-digital-age&quot;&gt;The digital age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot;&gt;Loss of humanity through transitions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chasing-perfection&quot;&gt;Chasing perfection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Essay on Typography by Eric Gill takes the reader back to the year 1930. The year when a conflict between two worlds came to its term. The machines of the industrial world finally took over the handicrafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typography of this industrial age was no longer handcrafted. Mass production and profit became more important. Quantity mattered more than the quality. The books and printed works in general lost a part of its humanity. The typefaces were not produced by craftsmen anymore. It was the machines printing and tying the books together now. The craftsmen had to let go of their craft and became a cog in the process. An extension of the industrial machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the victory of the industrialism didn’t mean that the craftsmen were completely extinct. The two worlds continued to coexist independently. Each recognising the good in the other — the power of industrialism and the humanity of craftsmanship. This was the second transition that would strip typography of a part of its humanity. We have to go 500 years back in time to meet the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-transition&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-first-transition&quot; aria-label=&quot;the first transition permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The first transition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar conflict emerged after the invention of the first printing press in Europe. Johannes Gutenberg invented movable type and used it to produce different compositions. His workshop could print up to 240 impressions per hour. Until then, the books were being copied by hand. All the books were handwritten and decorated with hand drawn ornaments and figures. A process of copying a book was long but each book, even a copy, was a work of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first printed books were, at first, perceived as inferior to the handwritten ones. They were smaller and cheaper to produce. Movable type provided the printers with flexibility that allowed them to print books in languages other than Latin. Gill describes the transition to industrialism as something that people needed and wanted. Something similar happened after the first printed books emerged. People wanted books in a language they understood and they wanted books they could take with them. They were hungry for knowledge and printed books satisfied this hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 800px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/4b190/42-line-bible.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 68.75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAOABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIEAQP/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABufUKs5i//8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIBEhARMf/aAAgBAQABBQLhdiLY2otmj//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABoQAAICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEUECEHH/2gAIAQEABj8CWqFJZKzhcP/EABoQAAICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABESExQVH/2gAIAQEAAT8htIzvAkKJdIZ1iOrKhtOD58i2UYQ//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABCPz//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQ/9oACAEDAQE/EGf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEP/aAAgBAgEBPxAn/8QAGxABAAIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFRQYH/2gAIAQEAAT8QURjCRbioVC2xo2WyVaV7jtwCCrbaU0oxx2BWbCVKxv5P/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/8ac56/42-line-bible.webp 240w,
/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/d3be9/42-line-bible.webp 480w,
/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/d00b9/42-line-bible.webp 800w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/09b79/42-line-bible.jpg 240w,
/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/7cc5e/42-line-bible.jpg 480w,
/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/4b190/42-line-bible.jpg 800w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/6d93cbc4956a854d4c4369f0e281e7f3/4b190/42-line-bible.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;42-line-bible.jpg&quot;
            title=&quot;42-line-bible.jpg&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 42–Line Bible, printed by Gutenberg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, through this transition, the book lost a large part of its humanity. The machine took over most of the process but craftsmanship was still a part of it. The typefaces were cut manually by the first punch cutters. The paper was made by hand. The illustrations and ornaments were still being hand drawn. These were the remains of the craftsmanship that went almost extinct in the times of Eric Gill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-digital-age&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-digital-age&quot; aria-label=&quot;the digital age permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The digital age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first transition took away a large part of humanity from written communication. Industrialisation, the second transition described by Eric Gill, took away most of what was left. But it’s the third transition that stripped it naked. Typefaces are faceless these days. They’re just fonts on our computers. Hardly anyone knows their stories. Hardly anyone cares. Flicking through thousands of typefaces and finding the “right one” is a matter of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new computer age the proliferation of typefaces and type manipulations represents a new level of visual pollution threatening our culture. Out of thousands of typefaces, all we need are a few basic ones, and trash the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Massimo Vignelli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typography is not about typefaces. It’s not about what looks best, it’s about what feels right. What communicates the message best. Typography, in its essence, is about the message. “Typographical design should perform optically what the speaker creates through voice and gesture of his thoughts.”, as El Lissitzky, a famous Russian typographer, put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot; aria-label=&quot;loss of humanity through transitions permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Loss of humanity through transitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each transition took away a part of humanity from written language. Handwritten books being the most humane form and the digital typefaces being the least. Overuse of Helvetica is a good example. Messages are being told in a typeface just because it’s a safe option. It’s always there. Everyone knows it but yet, nobody knows it. Stop someone on the street and ask him what Helvetica is? Ask a designer the same question. Ask him where it came from, when, why and who designed it. Most of them will fail to answer these questions. Most of them used it in their precious projects but they still don’t spot it in the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of the quality of a typeface is of the greatest importance for the functional, aesthetic and psychological effect.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;— Josef Mueller-Brockmann&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typefaces don’t look handmade these days. And that’s all right. They don’t have to. Industrialism took that away from them and we’re fine with it. We’ve traded that part of humanity for a process that produces more books that are easier to read. That can’t be bad. And it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humane typography will often be comparatively rough and even uncouth; but while a certain uncouthness does not seriously matter in humane works, uncouthness has no excuse whatever in the productions of the machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Eric Gill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve come close to “perfection” in the last five centuries. The letters are crisp and without rough edges. We print our compositions with high–precision printers on a high quality, machine made paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/66fdb/type-through-time.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 20%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAEABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFQABAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAT/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAv/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABtoJUin//xAAWEAEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACABD/2gAIAQEAAQUCMM//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEP/aAAgBAgEBPwEn/8QAFhAAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQ/9oACAEBAAY/Ahz/xAAaEAABBQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAhAAEQETFx/9oACAEBAAE/IbEutdR//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABB8D//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQ/9oACAEDAQE/EGf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQMf/aAAgBAgEBPxCD/8QAGBABAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARIUH/2gAIAQEAAT8QQNG9YkO1rqXP/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/8ac56/type-through-time.webp 240w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/d3be9/type-through-time.webp 480w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/e46b2/type-through-time.webp 960w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/e19c7/type-through-time.webp 1250w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/09b79/type-through-time.jpg 240w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/7cc5e/type-through-time.jpg 480w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/6a068/type-through-time.jpg 960w,
/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/66fdb/type-through-time.jpg 1250w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/eaa988471fd2b61a1d4d313d0d9a5d23/6a068/type-through-time.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;type-through-time.jpg&quot;
            title=&quot;type-through-time.jpg&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Type through 5 centuries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lost a part of ourselves because of this chase after perfection. We forgot about the craftsmanship along the way. And the worst part is that we don’t care. The transition to the digital age made that clear. We choose typefaces like clueless zombies. There’s no meaning in our work. Type sizes, leading, margins… It’s all just a few clicks or lines of code. The message isn’t important anymore. There’s no more “why” behind the “what”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;chasing-perfection&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chasing-perfection&quot; aria-label=&quot;chasing perfection permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chasing perfection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human beings aren’t perfect. Perfection is something that will always elude us. There will always be a small part of humanity in everything we do. No matter how small that part, we should make sure that it transcends the limits of the medium. We have to think about the message first. What typeface should we use and why? Does the typeface match the message and what we want to communicate with it? What will be the leading and why? Will there be more typefaces in our design? On what ground will they be combined? What makes our design unique and why? This is the part of humanity that is left in typography. It might be the last part. Are we really going to give it up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://matejlatin.co.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Matej Latin&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/design-notes/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age-9bd5c16199bd?ref=webdesignernews.com#.lygo82z0x&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Johannes Gutenberg: The Birth of Movable Type]]></title><description><![CDATA[German inventor Johannes Gutenberg developed a method of movable type and used it to create one of the western world’s first major printed books, the “Forty–Two–Line” Bible.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-birth-of-movable-type</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-birth-of-movable-type</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;German inventor Johannes Gutenberg developed a method of movable type and used it to create one of the western world’s first major printed books, the “Forty–Two–Line” Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Johannes Gensfleisch zur Laden zum Gutenberg&lt;/strong&gt; (c. 1398 – 1468) was a German blacksmith, goldsmith, printer, and publisher who introduced printing to Europe. His invention of mechanical movable type printing started the Printing Revolution and is widely regarded as the most important event of the modern period. It played a key role in the development of the Renaissance, Reformation, the Age of Enlightenment, and the Scientific revolution and laid the material basis for the modern knowledge-based economy and the spread of learning to the masses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;float-right&quot; style=&quot;width: 240px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 374px; &quot;&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/bf505/gutenberg.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 128.33333333333331%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAaABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQFAQP/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFxLehWIgM5WnDA2H//xAAcEAACAgMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABAwACERIhBBP/2gAIAQEAAQUC9DjBZi7LvvXIzmGxBcrU8lFDW3QgD6T/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEDAQE/AR//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAECAQE/AR//xAAdEAACAgEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIQERAhAiMVGh/9oACAEBAAY/AqxIfpYzcInqTkYyVp//xAAeEAEAAgICAwEAAAAAAAAAAAABACERMUFREGFxkf/aAAgBAQABPyEqtgKrlnaB4D+kM9XSRZ57yMzcdC61E18NzM9WH2NXsS+NsAoBPc05Wq8f/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAwwzz/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEDAQE/EB//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAECAQE/EB//xAAfEAEAAgICAgMAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMUFhEFFxgfD/2gAIAQEAAT8QZe2zt6PiYqDXmBN0LB5VnSYWvVocLdL9xtDlqmdub5WAj9B+6gFZa3ZtJWZr3ccF769FEWyhwLI6zecGHrx//9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source srcset=&quot;/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/8ac56/gutenberg.webp 240w,
/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/ad40e/gutenberg.webp 374w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot;&gt;
          &lt;source srcset=&quot;/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/09b79/gutenberg.jpg 240w,
/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/bf505/gutenberg.jpg 374w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; src=&quot;/static/3e20438298edd3a3fa746766d803f379/bf505/gutenberg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gutenberg&quot; title=&quot;Gutenberg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Johannes Gutenberg&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With his invention of the printing press, Gutenberg was the first European to use movable type printing, in around 1439. Among his many contributions to printing are: the invention of a process for mass-producing movable type; the use of oil-based ink; and the use of a wooden printing press similar to the agricultural screw presses of the period. His truly epochal invention was the combination of these elements into a practical system that allowed the mass production of printed books and was economically viable for printers and readers alike. Gutenberg’s method for making type is traditionally considered to have included a type metal alloy and a hand mould for casting type. The alloy was a mixture of lead, tin, and antimony that melted at a relatively low temperature for faster and more economical casting, cast well, and created a durable type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Renaissance Europe, the arrival of mechanical movable type printing introduced the era of mass communication which permanently altered the structure of society. The relatively unrestricted circulation of information — including revolutionary ideas — transcended borders, captured the masses in the Reformation and threatened the power of political and religious authorities; the sharp increase in literacy broke the monopoly of the literate elite on education and learning and bolstered the emerging middle class. Across Europe, the increasing cultural self-awareness of its people led to the rise of proto-nationalism, accelerated by the flowering of the European vernacular languages to the detriment of Latin’s status as lingua franca. In the 19th century, the replacement of the hand-operated Gutenberg-style press by steam-powered rotary presses allowed printing on an industrial scale, while Western-style printing was adopted all over the world, becoming practically the sole medium for modern bulk printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of movable type was a marked improvement on the handwritten manuscript, which was the existing method of book production in Europe, and upon woodblock printing, and revolutionized European book-making. Gutenberg’s printing technology spread rapidly throughout Europe and later the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His major work, the Gutenberg Bible (also known as the 42-line Bible), has been acclaimed for its high aesthetic and technical quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;printing-press&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#printing-press&quot; aria-label=&quot;printing press permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Printing Press&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 1439, Gutenberg was involved in a financial misadventure making polished metal mirrors (which were believed to capture holy light from religious relics) for sale to pilgrims to Aachen: in 1439 the city was planning to exhibit its collection of relics from Emperor Charlemagne but the event was delayed by one year due to a severe flood and the capital already spent could not be repaid. When the question of satisfying the investors came up, Gutenberg is said to have promised to share a “secret”. It has been widely speculated that this secret may have been the idea of printing with movable type. Also around 1439–1440, the Dutch Laurens Janszoon Coster came up with the idea of printing. Legend has it that the idea came to him “like a ray of light”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;float-left&quot; style=&quot;width: 240px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 754px; &quot;&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/cbfa4/printing-press.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 128.75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAaABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQCAwX/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAGVTqYwTAr1ARNAP//EABsQAAICAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAxEAEiEx/9oACAEBAAEFApNwbbWBmIkXpFCLxuMAwZBWUMKjFUV//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIP/aAAgBAwEBPwEf/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIP/aAAgBAgEBPwEf/8QAIBAAAgEDBAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERAiExIjJBUWFxkf/aAAgBAQAGPwJxUS6/g78lzwP2bZHpUDnswYRhH//EABwQAAIDAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExQZFR4f/aAAgBAQABPyHglk3AB0nrGMMqXYEgVsvZRojsjZaqBqH2ZIUNAe5FKmWl2PJ+GgNPCf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ08s8/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIP/aAAgBAwEBPxAf/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIP/aAAgBAgEBPxAf/8QAHxABAQACAgEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAITFBYYGRobHh/9oACAEBAAE/EL1wcj1uS+cMvt9hJoLu0nrgGxaxdBg5Ryp684T1lWbK9GoYtmIz6yaCgdBfD3z8YRTwoGHtznNDhdBQwVKsZsZ+AYgir0M//9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source srcset=&quot;/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/8ac56/printing-press.webp 240w,
/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/d3be9/printing-press.webp 480w,
/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/20eb0/printing-press.webp 754w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 754px) 100vw, 754px&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot;&gt;
          &lt;source srcset=&quot;/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/09b79/printing-press.jpg 240w,
/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/7cc5e/printing-press.jpg 480w,
/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/cbfa4/printing-press.jpg 754w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 754px) 100vw, 754px&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; src=&quot;/static/e2437eaf9c41cfbdb18f88a49699f24e/cbfa4/printing-press.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Early Printing Press&quot; title=&quot;Early Printing Press&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Early wooden printing press as depicted in 1568.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until at least 1444 he lived in Strasbourg, most likely in the St. Arbogast parish. It was in Strasbourg in 1440 that Gutenberg is said to have perfected and unveiled the secret of printing based on his research, mysteriously entitled Kunst und Aventur (art and enterprise). It is not clear what work he was engaged in, or whether some early trials with printing from movable type may have been conducted there. After this, there is a gap of four years in the record. In 1448, he was back in Mainz, where he took out a loan from his brother-in-law Arnold Gelthus, quite possibly for a printing press or related paraphernalia. By this date, Gutenberg may have been familiar with intaglio printing; it is claimed that he had worked on copper engravings with an artist known as the Master of Playing Cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1450, the press was in operation, and a German poem had been printed, possibly the first item to be printed there. Gutenberg was able to convince the wealthy moneylender Johann Fust for a loan of 800 guilders. Peter Schöffer, who became Fust’s son-in-law, also joined the enterprise. Schöffer had worked as a scribe in Paris and is believed to have designed some of the first typefaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;All that has been written to me about that marvelous man seen at Frankfurt is true. I have not seen complete Bibles but only a number of quires of various books of the Bible. The script was very neat and legible, not at all difficult to follow—your grace would be able to read it without effort, and indeed without glasses.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;—Future pope Pius II in a letter to Cardinal Carvajal, March 1455&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutenberg’s workshop was set up at Hof Humbrecht, a property belonging to a distant relative. It is not clear when Gutenberg conceived the Bible project, but for this he borrowed another 800 guilders from Fust, and work commenced in 1452. At the same time, the press was also printing other, more lucrative texts (possibly Latin grammars). There is also some speculation that there may have been two presses, one for the pedestrian texts, and one for the Bible. One of the profit-making enterprises of the new press was the printing of thousands of indulgences for the church, documented from 1454–55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1455 Gutenberg completed his 42-line Bible, known as the Gutenberg Bible. About 180 copies were printed, most on paper and some on vellum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;court-case&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#court-case&quot; aria-label=&quot;court case permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Court Case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some time in 1456, there was a dispute between Gutenberg and Fust, and Fust demanded his money back, accusing Gutenberg of misusing the funds. Meanwhile the expenses of the Bible project had proliferated, and Gutenberg’s debt now exceeded 20,000 guilders. Fust sued at the archbishop’s court. A November 1455 legal document records that there was a partnership for a “project of the books,” the funds for which Gutenberg had used for other purposes, according to Fust. The court decided in favor of Fust, giving him control over the Bible printing workshop and half of all printed Bibles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus Gutenberg was effectively bankrupt, but it appears he retained (or re-started) a small printing shop, and participated in the printing of a Bible in the town of Bamberg around 1459, for which he seems at least to have supplied the type. But since his printed books never carry his name or a date, it is difficult to be certain, and there is consequently a considerable scholarly debate on this subject. It is also possible that the large Catholicon dictionary, 300 copies of 754 pages, printed in Mainz in 1460, may have been executed in his workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Fust–Schöffer shop was the first in Europe to bring out a book with the printer’s name and date, the Mainz Psalter of August 1457, and while proudly proclaiming the mechanical process by which it had been produced, it made no mention of Gutenberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;later-life&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#later-life&quot; aria-label=&quot;later life permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Later Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1462, during a conflict between two archbishops, Mainz was sacked by archbishop Adolph von Nassau, and Gutenberg was exiled. An old man by now, he moved to Eltville where he may have initiated and supervised a new printing press belonging to the brothers Bechtermünze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 1465, Gutenberg’s achievements were recognized and he was given the title Hofmann (gentleman of the court) by von Nassau. This honor included a stipend, an annual court outfit, as well as 2,180 litres of grain and 2,000 litres of wine tax-free. It is believed he may have moved back to Mainz around this time, but this is not certain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutenberg died in 1468 and was buried in the Franciscan church at Mainz, his contributions largely unknown. This church and the cemetery were later destroyed, and Gutenberg’s grave is now lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1504, he was mentioned as the inventor of typography in a book by Professor Ivo Wittig. It was not until 1567 that the first portrait of Gutenberg, almost certainly an imaginary reconstruction, appeared in Heinrich Pantaleon’s biography of famous Germans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;printing-method-with-movable-type&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#printing-method-with-movable-type&quot; aria-label=&quot;printing method with movable type permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Printing Method With Movable Type&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutenberg’s early printing process, and what tests he may have made with movable type, are not known in great detail. His later Bibles were printed in such a way as to have required large quantities of type, some estimates suggesting as many as 100,000 individual sorts. Setting each page would take, perhaps, half a day, and considering all the work in loading the press, inking the type, pulling the impressions, hanging up the sheets, distributing the type, etc., it is thought that the Gutenberg–Fust shop might have employed as many as 25 craftsmen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/fa8cd/movable-type.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.25%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMEAQL/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB1T5JeycP/8QAGRABAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARAiFB/9oACAEBAAEFAuS4hZHPf//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABkQAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQABExUf/aAAgBAQAGPwImUs6//8QAGRABAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARIVFB/9oACAEBAAE/IRqzfh2KGcfJjkqGhio5yWNF3Ygip//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ0M//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARAP/aAAgBAwEBPxBkv//EABYRAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEf/aAAgBAgEBPxCETP/EAB0QAQEAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExUWGR4fD/2gAIAQEAAT8QR4MNpyWWe3EqqmnMnX3AGHHpcdEGRhEn15y3ZAQtP28DI0zP/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/8ac56/movable-type.webp 240w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/d3be9/movable-type.webp 480w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/e46b2/movable-type.webp 960w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/f992d/movable-type.webp 1440w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/882b9/movable-type.webp 1920w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/58cee/movable-type.webp 2288w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/09b79/movable-type.jpg 240w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/7cc5e/movable-type.jpg 480w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/6a068/movable-type.jpg 960w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/644c5/movable-type.jpg 1440w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/0f98f/movable-type.jpg 1920w,
/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/fa8cd/movable-type.jpg 2288w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/bd0272909c25e194b94dc89edc338274/6a068/movable-type.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;Movable metal type, and composing stick, descended from Gutenberg&amp;#39;s press. Photo by Willi Heidelbach. Licensed under CC BY 2.5&quot;
            title=&quot;Movable metal type, and composing stick, descended from Gutenberg&amp;#39;s press. Photo by Willi Heidelbach. Licensed under CC BY 2.5&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Movable metal type, and composing stick, descended from Gutenberg’s press. Photo by Willi Heidelbach. Licensed under CC BY 2.5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gutenberg’s technique of making movable type remains unclear. In the following decades, punches and copper matrices became standardized in the rapidly disseminating printing presses across Europe. Whether Gutenberg used this sophisticated technique or a somewhat primitive version has been the subject of considerable debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the standard process of making type, a hard metal punch (made by punchcutting, with the letter carved back to front) is hammered into a softer copper bar, creating a matrix. This is then placed into a hand-held mould and a piece of type, or “sort”, is cast by filling the mould with molten type-metal; this cools almost at once, and the resulting piece of type can be removed from the mould. The matrix can be reused to create hundreds, or thousands, of identical sorts so that the same character appearing anywhere within the book will appear very uniform, giving rise, over time, to the development of distinct styles of typefaces or fonts. After casting, the sorts are arranged into type-cases, and used to make up pages which are inked and printed, a procedure which can be repeated hundreds, or thousands, of times. The sorts can be reused in any combination, earning the process the name of “movable type”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invention of the making of types with punch, matrix and mold has been widely attributed to Gutenberg. However, recent evidence suggests that Gutenberg’s process was somewhat different. If he used the punch and matrix approach, all his letters should have been nearly identical, with some variations due to miscasting and inking. However, the type used in Gutenberg’s earliest work shows other variations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;It is a press, certainly, but a press from which shall flow in inexhaustible streams… Through it, god will spread his word.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;—Johannes Gutenberg&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2001, the physicist Blaise Agüera y Arcas and Princeton librarian Paul Needham, used digital scans of a Papal bull in the Scheide Library, Princeton, to carefully compare the same letters (types) appearing in different parts of the printed text. The irregularities in Gutenberg’s type, particularly in simple characters such as the hyphen, suggested that the variations could not have come from either ink smear or from wear and damage on the pieces of metal on the types themselves. While some identical types are clearly used on other pages, other variations, subjected to detailed image analysis, suggested that they could not have been produced from the same matrix. Transmitted light pictures of the page also appeared to reveal substructures in the type that could not arise from traditional punchcutting techniques. They hypothesized that the method may have involved impressing simple shapes to create alphabets in “cuneiform” style in a matrix made of some soft material, perhaps sand. Casting the type would destroy the mould, and the matrix would need to be recreated to make each additional sort. This could explain the variations in the type, as well as the substructures observed in the printed images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, they feel that “the decisive factor for the birth of typography”, the use of reusable moulds for casting type, might have been a more progressive process than was previously thought. They suggest that the additional step of using the punch to create a mould that could be reused many times was not taken until twenty years later, in the 1470s. Others have not accepted some or all of their suggestions, and have interpreted the evidence in other ways, and the truth of the matter remains very uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 1568 history by Hadrianus Junius of Holland claims that the basic idea of the movable type came to Gutenberg from Laurens Janszoon Coster via Fust, who was apprenticed to Coster in the 1430s and may have brought some of his equipment from Haarlem to Mainz. While Coster appears to have experimented with moulds and castable metal type, there is no evidence that he had actually printed anything with this technology. He was an inventor and a goldsmith. However, there is one indirect supporter of the claim that Coster might be the inventor. The author of the Cologne Chronicle of 1499 quotes Ulrich Zell, the first printer of Cologne, that printing was performed in Mainz in 1450, but that some type of printing of lower quality had previously occurred in the Netherlands. However, the chronicle does not mention the name of Coster, while it actually credits Gutenberg as the “first inventor of printing” in the very same passage (fol. 312). The first securely dated book by Dutch printers is from 1471, and the Coster connection is today regarded as a mere legend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 19th century printer and typefounder Fournier Le Jeune suggested that Gutenberg might not have been using type cast with a reusable matrix, but possibly wooden types that were carved individually. A similar suggestion was made by Nash in 2004. This remains possible, albeit entirely unproven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has also been questioned whether Gutenberg used movable types at all. In 2004, Italian professor Bruno Fabbiani claimed that examination of the 42-line Bible revealed an overlapping of letters, suggesting that Gutenberg did not in fact use movable type (individual cast characters) but rather used whole plates made from a system somewhat like a modern typewriter, whereby the letters were stamped successively into the plate and then printed. However, most specialists regard the occasional overlapping of type as caused by paper movement over pieces of type of slightly unequal height.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Origins of Social Stationery Lettering]]></title><description><![CDATA[Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-origins-of-social-stationery-lettering</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/the-origins-of-social-stationery-lettering</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique&lt;/strong&gt; senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. &lt;em&gt;Aenean ultricies mi vitae est.&lt;/em&gt; Mauris placerat eleifend leo. Quisque sit amet est et sapien ullamcorper pharetra. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum erat wisi, condimentum sed, commodo vitae, ornare sit amet, wisi. Aenean fermentum, elit eget tincidunt condimentum, eros ipsum rutrum orci, sagittis tempus lacus enim ac dui.  &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Donec non enim&lt;/a&gt; in turpis pulvinar facilisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/d9c39/image-3.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQBAgP/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABfVKJiSH/xAAaEAEAAwADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACAAESAyEy/9oACAEBAAEFAmsz1HyUUlWh3ENX/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPwE//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPwE//8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQESFRYf/aAAgBAQAGPwLpkqixPTj/xAAaEAACAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhMUGx/9oACAEBAAE/IUVVhS24c101z0lpaZnT0TI+Uf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQby//xAAXEQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREh/9oACAEDAQE/EFEYf//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQEf/aAAgBAgEBPxB1n//EABsQAQEBAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExUUGh/9oACAEBAAE/EDAqfPMB1RCeCH5mwNBUHOQq1qdGTO7KHHGIUBrp4u//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/8ac56/image-3.webp 240w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/d3be9/image-3.webp 480w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/e46b2/image-3.webp 960w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/f992d/image-3.webp 1440w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/62ed8/image-3.webp 1800w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/09b79/image-3.jpg 240w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/7cc5e/image-3.jpg 480w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/6a068/image-3.jpg 960w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/644c5/image-3.jpg 1440w,
/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/d9c39/image-3.jpg 1800w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/732bbf5c4fdcc63ac39e10f8f82a3435/6a068/image-3.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            title=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;header-level-2&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#header-level-2&quot; aria-label=&quot;header level 2 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Header Level 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donec non enim in turpis pulvinar facilisis. Ut felis. Praesent dapibus, neque id cursus faucibus, tortor neque egestas augue, eu vulputate magna eros eu erat. Aliquam erat volutpat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Vivamus magna. Cras in mi at felis aliquet congue. Ut a est eget ligula molestie gravida. Curabitur massa. Donec eleifend, libero at sagittis mollis, tellus est malesuada tellus, at luctus turpis elit sit amet quam. Vivamus pretium ornare est.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;— Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;header-level-3&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#header-level-3&quot; aria-label=&quot;header level 3 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Header Level 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. Aenean ultricies mi vitae est. Mauris placerat eleifend leo. Quisque sit amet est et sapien ullamcorper pharetra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token selector&quot;&gt;#header h1 a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; block&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 300px&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 80px&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donec non enim in turpis pulvinar facilisis. Ut felis. Praesent dapibus, neque id cursus faucibus, tortor neque egestas augue, eu vulputate magna eros eu erat. Aliquam erat volutpat. Nam dui mi, tincidunt quis, accumsan porttitor, facilisis luctus, metus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/71ba9417da76c390c80ad2f49c9c227d/cpu.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Test SVG&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Welcome to the Internet: You Don't Know Shit, Part 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[What happens if the CSS background-image URL is empty?]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/welcome-to-the-internet-you-don-t-know-shit-part-1</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/welcome-to-the-internet-you-don-t-know-shit-part-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 17:59:24 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was investigating if my controller was handling correctly post requests, when I noticed that it was being called twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the dev tools network panel showed there were indeed 2 requests, but the response size was different, and the second response preview was empty. According to Chrome the initiator of the request was some javascript at the bottom of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baffled, I called the front end developer over, but we quickly proved that it wasn’t due to any javascript. The request was fired with javascript disabled, but now the initiator was &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;index.html:infinity&lt;/code&gt;, infinity being the line of code where that happened. On my simpler example it actually shows the very last line of the html.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-everything-else-fails-old-style-debugging&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#when-everything-else-fails-old-style-debugging&quot; aria-label=&quot;when everything else fails old style debugging permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;When everything else fails: old style debugging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So…we started taking elements off the page, until it stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;style=&amp;quot;background-image: url(&amp;#39;&amp;#39;);&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; it’s interpreted as “the URL of the background image is an empty string, relative to the current URL”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can double check this by opening your tools and going to &lt;a href=&quot;/example/empty-background-image-url.html&quot;&gt;this example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initiator with javascript
&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 759px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/ef3e1/initiator-with-js.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 9.583333333333332%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAACCAIAAADXZGvcAAAACXBIWXMAAAsTAAALEwEAmpwYAAAAfklEQVQI12MwNjUFI3NjMyCyMDEzByJjUzMwaWJubnH89Plvv/9//Prrw9efT19/ePnu84s3nz58+fn9938GaztLFy9HJy8XFx83Wwc7U6AmCwtjYxMjY2NjIwNLc5NDJ87ef/7u+r2nj199ePb2y7O3nx8+f3f78avHrz4CAMs1P6nTSSRQAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/8ac56/initiator-with-js.webp 240w,
/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/d3be9/initiator-with-js.webp 480w,
/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/3440c/initiator-with-js.webp 759w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 759px) 100vw, 759px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/8ff5a/initiator-with-js.png 240w,
/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/e85cb/initiator-with-js.png 480w,
/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/ef3e1/initiator-with-js.png 759w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 759px) 100vw, 759px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/png&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/00f659ec40552dcbaf668f390027cd18/ef3e1/initiator-with-js.png&quot;
            alt=&quot;Initiator with javascript&quot;
            title=&quot;Initiator with javascript&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initiator without javascript
&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 842px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/99072/initiator-without-js.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 8.75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAACCAIAAADXZGvcAAAACXBIWXMAAAsTAAALEwEAmpwYAAAAeklEQVQI1yXC7QqCMBQAUB+oorbde3dlvW1QIL1N/4SiCS4rV2o17MsGHU6izRw1E6cY638GYjZmouQyW/ef4Xrv2/By56bybey7EN7D4/lNKEUVgQLSCgCQhJSzqUCCsRgtVllx6ja53R8uxbFx9c06n9tqV/ptWf8AoH9CtoIMyXcAAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/8ac56/initiator-without-js.webp 240w,
/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/d3be9/initiator-without-js.webp 480w,
/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/6366e/initiator-without-js.webp 842w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 842px) 100vw, 842px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/8ff5a/initiator-without-js.png 240w,
/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/e85cb/initiator-without-js.png 480w,
/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/99072/initiator-without-js.png 842w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 842px) 100vw, 842px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/png&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/8724162db473b51bfef502a4af72e9b6/99072/initiator-without-js.png&quot;
            alt=&quot;Initiator without javascript&quot;
            title=&quot;Initiator without javascript&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened is that I don’t enforce uploading images in the CMS, but if none is selected the URL is just null or empty. Writing &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;style=&amp;quot;background-image: url(&amp;#39;@(Model.Image?.Url)&amp;#39;);&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; is incorrect, the rule should not be in the style attribute if the URL is blank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution is to write a variable for the content of the style attribute, something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;c#&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-c#&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c#&quot;&gt;var imageUrl = Model.Image?.Url;
var style = imageUrl == null
    : string.Empty
    ? $&amp;quot;background-image: url(&amp;#39;{imageUrl}&amp;#39;);&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reference&quot; aria-label=&quot;reference permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=473528&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=473528&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Forestry.io]]></title><description><![CDATA[A review of Forestry.io for Hugo websites]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/forestry-io</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/forestry-io</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 06:01:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A reader of &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hugo-write-deploy-host&quot;&gt;my post on how I use Hugo&lt;/a&gt; pointed out in the comments that it’s now possible to write online Hugo posts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://forestry.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Forestry.io&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been playing with it and I’m currently using it to write this very post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as writing online goes it’s a big improvement over scribe.io. I’m just not sure that’s enough to make me switch to online writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the preview. Unfortunately, it’s not good enough as it doesn’t work with all Hugo’s shortcodes and custom ones either. What I would suggest instead is to have a test website. Forestry.io uses the development branch - you simply hook a new website under a test domain! Just make sure it’s not going to be indexed by search engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forestry.io is not responsive or mobile friendly either, so keep that in mind if you wish to blog from your mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I wish was also implemented is to be able to move files between folders. I organise them by year/month/day and it usually takes me more than a day to write a new blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lach of spel cheking when writin the post is very anoying. Not sure why but both Chrome standard spell checking and Chrome plugin Grammarly don’t work when writing the body of the post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, it feels like yet another application designed for Jekyll, that works for Hugo as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time I finished writing this post I also noticed that it came out of beta! I’m very happy to notice that it still has a free version, with community support and for less than 10 users. I was a bit concerned I was being used as a guinea pig and wasting my time here :)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Perfecting the Art of Perfection]]></title><description><![CDATA[Quisque cursus, metus vitae pharetra auctor, sem massa mattis sem, at interdum magna augue eget diam. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Morbi lacinia molestie dui. Praesent blandit dolor. Sed non quam. In vel mi sit amet augue congue elementum.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/perfecting-the-art-of-perfection</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/perfecting-the-art-of-perfection</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Quisque cursus, metus vitae pharetra auctor, sem massa mattis sem, at interdum magna augue eget diam. Vestibulum ante ipsum primis in faucibus orci luctus et ultrices posuere cubilia Curae; Morbi lacinia molestie dui. Praesent blandit dolor. Sed non quam. In vel mi sit amet augue congue elementum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/d9c39/image-2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.66666666666666%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGQAAAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQBAgMF/8QAFQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAaa8hyWBEP/EABoQAAIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAAMSBBP/2gAIAQEAAQUCbnLzNmfQpFcgt1WZn//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AVf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPwFH/8QAHRAAAAYDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECEBESISJxof/aAAgBAQAGPwKbkNYVwVWWWr63/8QAGxAAAgMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAITFRYZH/2gAIAQEAAT8h4/CbqGqoAvH2bwuzSXC1EA8C45//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAECAP/8QAFxEBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARMf/aAAgBAwEBPxATtq//xAAXEQEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEx/9oACAECAQE/EEeWb//EAB0QAQACAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESFRQXExYaH/2gAIAQEAAT8Q8maKQ0Osxgrk11gcIzHsBgv5BCW233uWAbGAD1qKtW1cq8z/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/8ac56/image-2.webp 240w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/d3be9/image-2.webp 480w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/e46b2/image-2.webp 960w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/f992d/image-2.webp 1440w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/62ed8/image-2.webp 1800w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/09b79/image-2.jpg 240w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/7cc5e/image-2.jpg 480w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/6a068/image-2.jpg 960w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/644c5/image-2.jpg 1440w,
/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/d9c39/image-2.jpg 1800w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/0249a8579cfb4088acaf23fcac068444/6a068/image-2.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            title=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. Aenean ultricies mi vitae est. Mauris placerat eleifend leo. Quisque sit amet est et sapien ullamcorper pharetra. Vestibulum erat wisi, condimentum sed, commodo vitae, ornare sit amet, wisi. Aenean fermentum, elit eget tincidunt condimentum, eros ipsum rutrum orci, sagittis tempus lacus enim ac dui. Donec non enim in turpis pulvinar facilisis. Ut felis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Praesent dapibus, neque id cursus faucibus, tortor neque egestas augue, eu vulputate magna eros eu erat. Aliquam erat volutpat. Nam dui mi, tincidunt quis, accumsan porttitor, facilisis luctus, metus.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Delete all google stored passwords]]></title><description><![CDATA[How to delete all the passwords stored in Google passwords https://passwords.google.com]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/delete-google-passwords</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/delete-google-passwords</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 22:02:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was trying to delete all the passwords stored in google at &lt;a href=&quot;https://passwords.google.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Google passwords&lt;/a&gt;, way too many to do manually!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couldn’t find a solution online so here is my easy one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://passwords.google.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Google passwords&lt;/a&gt;, sign in to your account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the development tools in your browser, usually with F12. I’ve used Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste the following code in the console.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Gets all the elements to be clicked to delete the passwords.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; a &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; document&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getElementsByClassName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;“dga”&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Click all the elements.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;length&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; i&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;a&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;i&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;click&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hugo: write, deploy, host]]></title><description><![CDATA[How to write content, deploy automatically and host your website]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/hugo-write-deploy-host</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/hugo-write-deploy-host</guid><pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 20:51:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this port I’ll show you how I write my posts, deploy them to the server, process them with &lt;a href=&quot;https://gohugo.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and host them on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.do.co/c/875cd23a5c97&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/a&gt; server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted this process to be as easy and quick as possible, with as few extra softwares and services as possible. There are a lot of solutions out there like Wercker but I didn’t want more things in my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;writing&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#writing&quot; aria-label=&quot;writing permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Writing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;local&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#local&quot; aria-label=&quot;local permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Local&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write the posts from IntelliJ IDEA, which is my IDE of choice. Screw Sublime, Atom and all the rest! It’s quite heavier but is worth it. You get spell checking, quite good live previews with the Multimarkdown plugin (shame the embedded HTML doesn’t render), git integration, and in general a powerful IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear I like Sublime and Atom, but every time I use them there is something wrong. Right now the terminal in Atom doesn’t work for me. There is an open issue for this but in the meantime you get a blinking unmovable cursor staring at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that, since Hugo is quite new, the tools haven’t caught up with its popularity yet. Intellij is flexible enough to allow you to have shortcuts &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jetbrains.com/help/idea/2016.1/live-templates.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;live templates&lt;/a&gt; for your shortcodes. E.g.:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;xml&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-xml&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-xml&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;.shortcode&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;{{&lt;span class=&quot;token entity named-entity&quot; title=&quot;&amp;lt;&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; $SHORTCODE$ &lt;span class=&quot;token entity named-entity&quot; title=&quot;&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;}}&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;A Hugo shortcode&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;toReformat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;false&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;toShortenFQNames&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;SHORTCODE&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;expression&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;defaultValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;alwaysStopAt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;option&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;OTHER&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token attr-name&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token attr-value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation attr-equals&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;true&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;/&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token tag&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows me to type &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.s&lt;/code&gt;, press enter (if the live template &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.shortcode&lt;/code&gt; is selected), type the name of the shortcode and its parameters and press enter to keep typing without having to type too many symbols or having to move your cursor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep switching between IntelliJ and the localhost page on my browser, where my hugo server is showing how the end result will be (just launch “hugo server” from the root folder). If you have the page open you don’t even need to refresh it thanks to Hugo’s live reload feature (and don’t even have to save the file since IntelliJ does it when it loses focus). This is very quick to do, which is particularly nice when you want to make final tweaks to make sure your post will display as you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;online&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#online&quot; aria-label=&quot;online permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Online&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are using Github and want to write from your browser, or you are not at home, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://prose.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;prose.io&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a software developed for Jekyll, but works just fine with Hugo. You get some nice shortcuts to format your text with markdown in case you are not too familiar with it. It also allows you to upload images which are committed to your repo immediately. I don’t find it quite as powerful as IntelliJ but it’s a nice option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Draga/go-web/blob/master/_prose.yml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;my prose configuration&lt;/a&gt; to get you started. It’s important to know that prose.io can only generate content with yaml metadata. You will have to configure Hugo to do the same by adding &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;MetaDataFormat: yaml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve looked at many more free online content editor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sofish.github.io/pen/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;sofish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webhook.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;webhook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.contentful.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;contentful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://prismic.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;prismic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stackedit.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;stackedit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dillinger.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;dillinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found them actually extremely good…just not very compatible with Hugo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I couldn’t find any online resource to write and preview Hugo content, so editing content locally and preview it with Hugo server is still the best option for me. I reckon you could host a test environment to preview your draft, deploying with a different branch, by adding &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;-buildDrafts&lt;/code&gt; to your &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;hugo server&lt;/code&gt; commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully some tool that works perfectly with Hugo will come out soon. Spf13, the creator of Hugo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://discuss.gohugo.io/t/web-based-editor/155/41&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;is thinking about creating one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;deployment&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#deployment&quot; aria-label=&quot;deployment permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Deployment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can deploy my website in 2 ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push you branch to the repo on the server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push the master branch to the main repo. In my case this is on Github but can work with pretty much anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These both trigger a small script which I’ve adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-deploy-a-hugo-site-to-production-with-git-hooks-on-ubuntu-14-04&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;this tutorial on Digitalocean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token shebang important&quot;&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Better be specific rather than using $HOME because it wouldn&apos;t work with all users.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token assign-left variable&quot;&gt;GIT_REPO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/home/draga/go-web
&lt;span class=&quot;token assign-left variable&quot;&gt;WORKING_DIRECTORY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$GIT_REPO&lt;/span&gt;/public
&lt;span class=&quot;token assign-left variable&quot;&gt;PUBLIC_WWW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/home/draga/public_html
&lt;span class=&quot;token assign-left variable&quot;&gt;BACKUP_WWW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/home/draga/backup_html

&lt;span class=&quot;token builtin class-name&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; -e

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Clean working dir.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rm&lt;/span&gt; -rf &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$WORKING_DIRECTORY&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Backup current website. Use -z if moving across network to save bandwidth.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rsync&lt;/span&gt; -aq &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$PUBLIC_WWW&lt;/span&gt;/ &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$BACKUP_WWW&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Restore backup if an error occurs from now on.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token builtin class-name&quot;&gt;trap&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;echo &apos;A problem occurred.  Reverting to backup.&apos;; rsync -aq --del &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$BACKUP_WWW&lt;/span&gt;/ &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$PUBLIC_WWW&lt;/span&gt;; rm -rf &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$WORKING_DIRECTORY&lt;/span&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt; EXIT

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# fetch repo to make sure it&apos;s up to date if working with remote webhook.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token builtin class-name&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$GIT_REPO&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;git&lt;/span&gt; fetch
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;git&lt;/span&gt; checkout origin/master
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Build the website. GO HUGO!&lt;/span&gt;
/usr/bin/hugo -s &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$GIT_REPO&lt;/span&gt; -d &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$WORKING_DIRECTORY&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Mirror the output of Hugo to the directory where the website is hosted.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Use -c to copy only files that have changed to avoid messing with webhost caches.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Use -z if moving across network to save bandwidth.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rsync&lt;/span&gt; -aqc --delete &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$WORKING_DIRECTORY&lt;/span&gt;/ &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$PUBLIC_WWW&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Ask Google webmaster tools to parse your sitemap.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;curl&lt;/span&gt; https://google.com/webmasters/sitemaps/ping?sitemap&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;https://stefano.chiodino.uk/sitemap.xml
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;curl&lt;/span&gt; https://www.bing.com/ping?sitemap&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;https%3A%2F%2Fstefano.chiodino.uk/sitemap.xml
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Disable trap.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token builtin class-name&quot;&gt;trap&lt;/span&gt; - EXIT&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the method described in the tutorial above for a while, but it bothered me to push twice since I had to type the password for my ssh key (I’ve disabled the password access to the server and can now only be accessed with the key). Also what if I wasn’t home or wanted to use prose.io?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution: git(hub) webhooks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adnanh/webhook&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;github.com/adnanh/webhook&lt;/a&gt;, little software written in go, you can have you server listen on a port and execute a script when invoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I currently have it connecting in https, with a secret key, and executing the script when the master branch is pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can even use Github itself to edit my posts. Pretty neat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;hosting&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#hosting&quot; aria-label=&quot;hosting permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Hosting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this was the &lt;del&gt;long&lt;/del&gt; fun part. I wanted it all so it took a lot of learning, hence the fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard of nginx a lot and some research showed that it seems to be the go-to solution. Here are some, more performance related, details of how it performs for me: &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/server-load-test&quot;&gt;server load test&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve then enabled the pagespeed module which is very complex and heavy, but definitively worth it!
The website now scores &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/pagespeed/insights/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fstefano.chiodino.uk%2F&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;100/100 in Google PageSpeed&lt;/a&gt;, both in mobile and desktop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I score 99/100 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://gtmetrix.com/reports/stefano.chiodino.uk/FsGkxV4j&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GTmetrix&lt;/a&gt; just because there is a bug in the pagespeed module (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pagespeed/ngx_pagespeed/issues/1064&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;1064&lt;/a&gt;) and the very header is added twice, and for some reason GTmetrix seems to think that is not there…? Or maybe is because pagespeed seems to add it on subsequent reloads. Another small penalty is for the G analytics code being cached for just 2 hours, it’s out of my control and don’t think is worth self hosting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YSlow seems to be mostly concerned of the lack of CDN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find all the scripts that I’ve used to set up my server on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Draga/serverScripts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. They are ordered in the same way they are in the filesystem, so you should get the idea. There is a script to install nginx with the brotli and pagespeed module, directives to use webhook as a service, the entire nginx configuration, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Server load test]]></title><description><![CDATA[Load testing a $5 Digitalocean server]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/server-load-test</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/server-load-test</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 13:50:14 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.do.co/c/875cd23a5c97&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Digitalocean&lt;/a&gt; hosting and decided to host this blog on it. I’m running a &lt;span class=&quot;katex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;katex-mathml&quot;&gt;&lt;math xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML&quot;&gt;&lt;semantics&gt;&lt;mrow&gt;&lt;mn&gt;5&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;mi mathvariant=&quot;normal&quot;&gt;/&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;m&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;n&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;h&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;s&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;r&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;v&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;r&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mo separator=&quot;true&quot;&gt;,&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;r&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;d&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;r&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;p&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;l&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;s&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;h&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;y&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;c&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;l&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;l&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;i&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mo separator=&quot;true&quot;&gt;,&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mi&gt;w&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;i&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;h&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;1&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;mi&gt;C&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;P&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;U&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mo separator=&quot;true&quot;&gt;,&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mn&gt;512&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;mi&gt;M&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;B&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;f&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;r&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;m&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mo separator=&quot;true&quot;&gt;,&lt;/mo&gt;&lt;mn&gt;20&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;mi&gt;G&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;B&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;S&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;S&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;D&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;n&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;d&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mn&gt;1&lt;/mn&gt;&lt;mi&gt;T&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;B&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;f&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;b&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;a&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;n&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;d&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;w&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;i&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;d&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;h&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi mathvariant=&quot;normal&quot;&gt;.&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;Y&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;o&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;u&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;v&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;n&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;g&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;e&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;mi&gt;t&lt;/mi&gt;&lt;/mrow&gt;&lt;annotation encoding=&quot;application/x-tex&quot;&gt;5 / month server, or droplet as they call it, with 1 CPU, 512 MB of ram, 20 GB SSD and 1 TB of bandwidth. You even get&lt;/annotation&gt;&lt;/semantics&gt;&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;katex-html&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;base&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;strut&quot; style=&quot;height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;5/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02778em;&quot;&gt;ser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.03588em;&quot;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02778em;&quot;&gt;er&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mpunct&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mspace&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02778em;&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;ro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.01968em;&quot;&gt;pl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;eyc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.01968em;&quot;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mpunct&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mspace&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02691em;&quot;&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.13889em;&quot;&gt;CP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.10903em;&quot;&gt;U&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mpunct&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mspace&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;512&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.05017em;&quot;&gt;MB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.10764em;&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02778em;&quot;&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mpunct&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mspace&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.05764em;&quot;&gt;GBSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02778em;&quot;&gt;D&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.05017em;&quot;&gt;TB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.10764em;&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;ban&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.02691em;&quot;&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.22222em;&quot;&gt;Y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;u&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.03588em;&quot;&gt;v&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:0.03588em;&quot;&gt;g&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mord mathnormal&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;10 credit when you sign up, sweet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may look down on a $5 machine but I’ve found it to be more than enough for my need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m serving “static” content that has been generated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://gohugo.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently ran some load testing at work for a newly launched website so I decided to test this $5 server. I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://loader.io&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;loader.io&lt;/a&gt; since its basic usage is free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-test&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-test&quot; aria-label=&quot;the test permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server responds to a certain number of clients every second for a full minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of the users must receive the page in &amp;#x3C; 5 secs. Only the html is loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;plain-html&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#plain-html&quot; aria-label=&quot;plain html permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Plain HTML&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10.000 requests a second! (that is the maximum that loaded.io goes on a free plan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;enable-strong-https&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#enable-strong-https&quot; aria-label=&quot;enable strong https permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Enable strong HTTPS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=https%3A%2F%2Fstefano.chiodino.uk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-vivaldi-spatnav-clickable=&quot;1&quot;&gt;How strong you say?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected enabling https is taking its toll. The server can’t accommodate less than half of the requests, “just” 4.000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-on-pagespeed-on-strong-https&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#full-on-pagespeed-on-strong-https&quot; aria-label=&quot;full on pagespeed on strong https permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Full on PageSpeed on strong HTTPS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve then enabled Google’s PageSpeed module for Nginx and enabled every performance related filter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve enabled 27 extra filters on top of the 34 enabled by default, leaving just 7 out that were just for compatibility or counterproductive, hell I’ve even enabled the filter to make the G analytics script async when it’s already implemented that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Result: a quite dramatic 150 clients/sec 😀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of filters that I’ve enabled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;nginx&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-nginx&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-nginx&quot;&gt;pagespeed EnableFilters responsive_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters outline_css&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters outline_javascript&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters move_css_above_scripts&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters move_css_to_head&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters rewrite_style_attributes&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters prioritize_critical_css&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters make_google_analytics_async&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters canonicalize_javascript_libraries&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters inline_google_font_css&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters local_storage_cache&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters convert_to_webp_animated&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters insert_image_dimensions&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters inline_preview_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters resize_mobile_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters remove_comments&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters collapse_whitespace&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters elide_attributes&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters extend_cache_pdfs&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters sprite_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters rewrite_domains&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters trim_urls&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters remove_quotes&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters defer_javascript&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters dedup_inlined_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters lazyload_images&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
pagespeed EnableFilters insert_dns_prefetch&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;brotli-max-compression&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#brotli-max-compression&quot; aria-label=&quot;brotli max compression permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Brotli (max compression)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just add Accept-Encoding: br to loader.io request headers and… 75 clients / sec. Not bad considering that I’ve enabled the maximum (11) level of compression!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;..and, if you are curious about the compression, my homepage file sizes are (method from &lt;a href=&quot;https://hacks.mozilla.org/2015/11/better-than-gzip-compression-with-brotli&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mozilla’s brotli post &lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Algorithm&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Size&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;none&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9508&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gzip&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3344&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;brotli&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2732&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Brief History of Typography]]></title><description><![CDATA[Morbi in sem quis dui placerat ornare. Pellentesque odio nisi, euismod in, pharetra a, ultricies in, diam. Sed arcu. Cras consequat.]]></description><link>https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/a-brief-history-of-typography</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://stefano.chiodino.uk/posts/a-brief-history-of-typography</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique&lt;/strong&gt; senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. &lt;em&gt;Aenean ultricies mi vitae est.&lt;/em&gt; Mauris placerat eleifend leo. Quisque sit amet est et sapien ullamcorper pharetra. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum erat wisi, condimentum sed, commodo vitae, ornare sit amet, wisi. Aenean fermentum, elit eget tincidunt condimentum, eros ipsum rutrum orci, sagittis tempus lacus enim ac dui.  &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Donec non enim&lt;/a&gt; in turpis pulvinar facilisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/d9c39/image-0.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.66666666666666%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAwAE/8QAFgEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAgED/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFYTebWei//xAAcEAABAwUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAAIhAxESMkH/2gAIAQEAAQUCBQkPxvKp6d//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAZEAACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARAhYXH/2gAIAQEABj8CmhaPp//EABwQAQADAQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExQWFxkf/aAAgBAQABPyG2s3zDlwtPso2l+4urVTU7nen9iDmYif/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQVy//xAAWEQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAASH/2gAIAQMBAT8QShD/xAAWEQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAASH/2gAIAQIBAT8QbpT/xAAdEAEAAgIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMUFRYXGR/9oACAEBAAE/EBqFjmHHCQKTXget+R0cJnJjlDcKlul/L4gKW10tG7HcIO4FdP2f/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
          &lt;source
              srcset=&quot;/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/8ac56/image-0.webp 240w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/d3be9/image-0.webp 480w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/e46b2/image-0.webp 960w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/f992d/image-0.webp 1440w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/62ed8/image-0.webp 1800w&quot;
              sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
              type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
            /&gt;
          &lt;source
            srcset=&quot;/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/09b79/image-0.jpg 240w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/7cc5e/image-0.jpg 480w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/6a068/image-0.jpg 960w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/644c5/image-0.jpg 1440w,
/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/d9c39/image-0.jpg 1800w&quot;
            sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
            type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
          /&gt;
          &lt;img
            class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
            src=&quot;/static/b3e5e61f7fb8888ba76b502242e27bd0/6a068/image-0.jpg&quot;
            alt=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            title=&quot;Nulla faucibus vestibulum eros in tempus. Vestibulum tempor imperdiet velit nec dapibus&quot;
            loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
            style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
          /&gt;
        &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;header-level-2&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#header-level-2&quot; aria-label=&quot;header level 2 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Header Level 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donec non enim in turpis pulvinar facilisis. Ut felis. Praesent dapibus, neque id cursus faucibus, tortor neque egestas augue, eu vulputate magna eros eu erat. Aliquam erat volutpat. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit. Vivamus magna. Cras in mi at felis aliquet congue. Ut a est eget ligula molestie gravida. Curabitur massa. Donec eleifend, libero at sagittis mollis, tellus est malesuada tellus, at luctus turpis elit sit amet quam. Vivamus pretium ornare est.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;— Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;header-level-3&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#header-level-3&quot; aria-label=&quot;header level 3 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Header Level 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aliquam tincidunt mauris eu risus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pellentesque habitant morbi tristique senectus et netus et malesuada fames ac turpis egestas. Vestibulum tortor quam, feugiat vitae, ultricies eget, tempor sit amet, ante. Donec eu libero sit amet quam egestas semper. Aenean ultricies mi vitae est. Mauris placerat eleifend leo. Quisque sit amet est et sapien ullamcorper pharetra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token selector&quot;&gt;#header h1 a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; block&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 300px&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; 80px&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vestibulum erat wisi, condimentum sed, commodo vitae, ornare sit amet, wisi. Aenean fermentum, elit eget tincidunt condimentum, eros ipsum rutrum orci, sagittis tempus lacus enim ac dui. Donec non enim in turpis pulvinar facilisis. Ut felis. Praesent dapibus, neque id cursus faucibus, tortor neque egestas augue, eu vulputate magna eros eu erat. Aliquam erat volutpat. Nam dui mi, tincidunt quis, accumsan porttitor, facilisis luctus, metus.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>